HINA TILLAT Resume

Hina Tillat (Ms)

Contact No: +92 332 9942274 Email: hinatillat@yahoo.com

PROFILE:

I have experience in diverse aspects of programme/project management within education sector, humanitarian & development sector; including designing and implementing projects, managing budgets, managing and implementing activities, training and capacity building, managing contracts and sub-grants, supervising and mentoring teams and implementing partners, research and analyses. This has put me in contact with variety of people from different cultures and back grounds including children, refugees/IDPs, students, volunteers, and people with psychological problems, implementing partners from a wide range of educational institutes, NGOs, international donors, government departments and universities. My current position is culmination of all my skill & knowledge into working towards stability, development and peace in FATA.

CAREER HISTORY:

CURRENT:

1. Social Sector Specialist, (World Bank) Governance Support Project of Multi Donor Trust Fund-MDTF- FATA Secretariat, Peshawar, Pakistan (October 2012 till date)

I am part of a core team at the Implementation Support Unit (ISU-FATA) of the Post Crisis Need Assessment (PCNA) working under the Multi Donor Trust Fund.

Currently I am the focal person for FATA Development Indicator Household Survey; working with Pakistan Institute of Development Economics (PIDE) and Institute of Management Sciences.

Apart from this recently completed mapping of investment trends in FATA over time period 2010-2013 against PCNA recommendations.

I am also part of core team working on a 10 years governance program relating to governance reforms in FATA.

Another achievement has been part of the organizing team of the First ever Pre Development Budget consultation for FATA.

My other responsibilities include:

- Assist and advice the PCNA Coordinator in designing and implementing Annual Work Plan within the structure of Strategic Transitional Results Framework (STRF) of PCNA and its relevant strategic objectives in consultation with the stakeholders;
- Carrying-out capacity gap analysis of the Line Departments for Education, Health, Social Welfare and Population Welfare
- Take leading role in social sector related studies, surveys and other activities as required by the World Bank
- Designing, preparing and sequencing social sector projects based on the PCNA recommendations in association with the Line Departments. Assist the line departments in execution of these projects.
- Conducting trainings, awareness programs and develops guidelines for partners/line departments and other MDTF projects as required
- •Support Communication Specialist for devising communication strategy, knowledge products and dissemination of results
- Interacting and liaising with Development Partners and arrange regular updates, briefing etc.
- Preparing reports, briefs and monitoring progress to ensure three cross cutting issues/themes of PCNS i.e. peace building and crisis sensitivity; gender and capacity building are integrated in the process;
- Analyse funding trends by the Government of Pakistan and donors against PCNA recommendation in respective sectors

- Give policy recommendations based on research and analyses and other duties per requirement of PCNA process
- 2. Visiting Faculty at Institute of Management Sciences, Peshawar (January, 2013 till date) I am a visiting faculty member/ lecturer for the Masters Programme of Development Studies. Currently I am taking the subjects 'Gender and Development' and 'Managing Non Governmental Organizations'.

PREVIOUS:

1. AusAID Mentor, University of Melbourne, Australia (Dec 2011 till July 2012)

As an AusAID Mentor my main responsibilities were:

- Make initial email contact with AusAID scholarship students before their arrival at the university and assist in preparations
- Respond to emails; queries, questions and provide information to students and refer to relevant International Student Support
- Support pre-departure orientation

Contact new AusAID students/mentees on arrival and provide orientation

- Provide information and assistance on the services and facilities helping them in adjusting in the new country
- Coordinate with various departments within university to accommodate new arrivals and support in addressing issues
- 2. Training Coordinator (Child Protection) Emergency Response and Recovery Program ERRP, Save the Children (alliance of US, UK and Sweden) based in Islamabad (with frequent visits to the Internally Displaced Persons and flood affected areas) Pakistan. July 2010-Nov 2010:

Under the supervision of Child Protection Manager & Advisor, my job was to look after the training component of the child protection unit across programme. My responsibilities included:

- Ensuring proper design, implementation and facilitation of all Save the Children Child Protection Trainings in program areas.
- Conduct training needs assessment (TNA)
- Prepare and administer plan for child protection trainings for the implementing partners
- Prepare training material and organizing trainings as per finalized plan.
- Supervise, mentor and guide a team of Child Protection Trainers
- Provide orientation and training to Child Protection Coordinators, Monitoring and Evaluation staff, Project Officers, Community Mobilizers and Child Friendly Space supervisors, Government officials and others on various issues including setting up and managing a Child Friendly Space, Child Rights, Child Participation, Child Protection (including the Child Protection Policy), Community Participation, identification and referral of vulnerable children.
- develop and manage participants' and trainees data base Participate in Child Protection assessment and analysis process.
- Develop weekly and monthly training reports as well as a consolidated training report at the end of tenure.
- Represent Save the Children at the Child Protection Cluster meetings, at UNICEF and other forums as required.
- Work as Child Protection trainer for UNICEF or other partners as required
- Initiate a child protection training manual
- 3. Scholarships & Apprenticeships Manager; FATA Development Programme-Livelihoods Development (FDP-LD) International Rescue Committee (IRC), May 2008-July 2010:

Under the USAID funded programme for Lower FATA, being part of the technical team of Component 1, I started the scholarships and apprenticeships schemes and:

- Designed & Managed the overall scholarships/apprenticeships schemes including correspondence with students and relevant departments, student's selection and enrollment finalization and follow up as well as work with Implementing partners
- Supervised the field staff, coordinated with relevant units & line departments, supported in identification of implementing partners/educational institutes for scholarships
- Managed the contracts and sub-grants by implementing partners (IPs)
- Supervised the pilot programme on career counseling and apprenticeships, skills training and career development counseling including: review, edit and approve manuals/training modules and documents developed by IPs, identify gaps and initiate remedial action, follow-up on students/apprentices progress & problems.
- Prepared and managed budgets of the IPs in collaboration with finance and M & E Departments
- Develop weekly/monthly/quarterly/annual budgets, reports and work plans, in collaboration with finance and M & E staff
- Managed data entry and updates into the USAID GIS Activity Tracking System (ATS)
- Develop and manage applicants, scholars and trainees' data base
- Presented the FDP-LD program at national and international forums
- Coordinated with HR in hiring and training staff
- Worked in collaboration with logistics, finance, grants/compliance, communication units, auditors etc for the smooth running of program and transparent achievements of programme objectives.
- Presented IRC and the programme on national and regional forums

4. Interpreter, International Labour Organization (ILO-UN) (April 2008):

I assisted a team of-international and national-evaluators during evaluation of an ILO funded project. The project focused on street working children and their educational needs. During the tenure I:

- Visited different project areas in Peshawar district to provide support in evaluating the program field centers, evaluation of on-going teacher's training and gauge its effectiveness
- Interviewing teachers & trainers, meeting with implementing partners/local NGOs, meetings/interviews with project beneficiaries/students while interviewing and recording all stakeholders' impressions & feedback including Elementary Education Foundation, PITE (Provincial institute for teacher's training), provincial minister of education (NWFP) and other line departments staff
- Translated conversation and material for the evaluators including collection and interpretation of the program data
- Provided support in preparation of final report.

5. Field Manager, Women Empowerment Project, International Rescue Committee (IRC) Aug 2007-Mar 2008:

As Field manager for this Afghan refugee (women) project I was responsible to:

- Supervise and monitor the project activities & staff
- Budgeting and financial monitoring
- Planning & reporting activities
- Design and conduct trainings on life skills to a variety of audience including technical/vocational instructors from government & private vocational & technical institutes, NGO staff and government officials
- Develop and manage participants' and trainees data base
- Liaison and coordination with organization and government institutes
- Follow up with beneficiaries and stake holders for evaluation

- Procurement and other logistic arrangement-like hiring buildings, purchase of material, arrangements for training etc
- Presenting the programme on different forums
- Identification of gaps and pro-active steps for improvement
- Identification of staff training needs and other management duties including successful closure of project.

6. Psycho-Social Counselor, Durable Solutions Programme-Women Empowerment Unit, IRC from March 2006 – August 2007

As a Psycho-social Counselor:

- Provided psychosocial counseling to Afghan Refugee women- in groups, individually and to families
- Conducted awareness sessions on gender and gender based violence, human rights, women and children rights etc
- Supervised field based skill-centers and field staff
- Designed and conducted trainings on life skills and counseling
- Developed a manual for psychosocial counseling as well as adapted an Urdu and Pashto manual for volunteer-psychosocial counselor
- Supported project manager in office activities, preparation of reports and work plans etc,
- Established women empowerment committees and trained the committee members
- Identified and mentored female volunteers for informal counseling within Afghan refugee camps

7. Teaching Experience

- i. I worked as Teacher at Beacon House School System, Peshawar (Sep 2003 to March 2006) My major Responsibilities included lesson planning, conducting lessons, identification of learning disabilities and training needs, identification of emotional problems and providing child/parents/family counseling, teaching through special techniques, develop test/exam papers, conduct exams, mark papers and prepare results, coordinate with staff and parents for child's development, support management/administration etc. Participate in teachers training and provide feedback to subject coordinator on various teaching methodologies, support in curriculum development and testing etc.
- ii. I worked as **Teacher at Peshawar Grammar School, Peshawar (Oct 2002 to August 2003).** Initially I worked as trainee teacher under supervision, latter on I worked as subject and class teacher. My responsibilities included preparation of lesson plans and conduct lessons, identified learning disabilities and emotional problems and found solutions, coordinated with parents, keeping record of student's progress, support in curriculum modification and assist administration.

8. Internships & Volunteer Experience

i. South Asia Program Support Intern/volunteer, International Support Program, Oxfam Australia (National Office, Melbourne, Australia) Sep 2011-Dec 2011:

My responsibilities included:

- Conducting research and analysis on economic justice and food security related issues and statistics with in Sri Lanka and the broader region
- Identify potential donors for Oxfam Australia's development programs in South Asia and develop a data base
- Refine and complete program reports, case studies and other documents received from countries in South Asia.

- Support the Program Quality and Funding Coordinators to develop concept notes/proposals for Oxfam Australia's Sri Lanka program.
- Write program/project level case studies, compiling information from several sources
- General administrative tasks as needed by the unit.
- ii. I worked as **Counseling Internee at Dost Welfare Foundation**; a **Peshawar based N.G.O** working for the rehabilitation of drug-addicts: I received training in counseling techniques, under the supervision of in-charge Counselor; provided counseling to drug addicts, consulted with doctors, identified relapses and suggested treatment for improvement.
- iii. As **Counselor Intern at the Special Education Complex, Peshawar**, I gained supervised experience in counseling of special children, identifying their special needs and supported them in adjustment to their class room.

EDUCATION:

- Masters in Development Studies, Melbourne University, Australia (2011-2012)
- Certificate course on Project Design and Proposal Readiness, Local Livelihoods Ltd. UK (2009)
- M.Sc Psychology, University of Peshawar, Pakistan (2001-2002)
- Bachelor of Arts, University of Peshawar, Pakistan (1998-2000)

COMPUTER SKILLS:

Proficient in MS Office; MS Word, MS Excel, MS Power-Point, Internet, Out-look Beginner in MS Project

LANGUAGES:

Fluent in English, Urdu, Pashto Beginner in Dari, Panjabi, Farsi and Arabic

REFREENCES:

Available on request